Zetzel, Elizabeth Rosenberg, 1907-1970. Papers, 1943-1970: A Finding Aid
Papers, 1943-1970
82-M259
Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute
Elizabeth Rosenberg Zetzel, 1907-1970
3 cartons, 1 file box
Correspondence, lectures, course notes, biographical data, etc., of Elizabeth R. Zetzel, psychiatrist and psychoanalyst.
Accession number: 82-M259
This collection was given to the Schlesinger Library by Dr. Louis Zetzel in December 1982.
BIOGRAPHY
ERZ, psychiatrist and psychoanalyst, was born in New York City, March 17, 1907, the daughter of James and Babette (Herman) Rosenberg. She was graduated from the Ethical Culture High School in 1924 and from Smith College with an A.B. in economics in 1928. She attended the London School of Economics as graduate student; while there, she became interested in medicine. She took her degree in medicine from London University in 1937, completed her training in psychoanalysis in 1938 and qualified as a psychiatrist at the Maudsley Hospital in 1939. She was employed as an army psychiatrist in the Royal Army Medical Corps during World War II and after demobilization worked at the London Institute of Psychoanalysis and the Maudsley Hospital. She married Erich Guttman, neurologist and psychiatrist, in 1944 and, after his death in 1948, returned to the United States with their infant son, James. In June 1949 she married Dr. Louis Zetzel, a widower with two daughters. In Boston, her professional career combined research, teaching and psychiatric practice. She lectured at Harvard Medical School, 1950-1970, at Simmons College School of Social Work, 1953-1960, and was director of the Psychotherapy Study Center of the Massachusetts Mental Health Center, 1963-1970. Having registered and been lisensed as a physician in Massachusetts in January 1950, ERZ was appointed psychiatrist at the Massachusetts General Hospital, 1951-1970, and at McLean' Hospital, 1958-1965, and analyst at the Boston Psychoanalytic Society and Institute, 1951-1970. She was a member of Phi Beta Kappa, the International Psycho-Analytical Association (of which she was vice-president at the time of her death), and the American Psychoanalytic Association, and a Fellow of the American Psychiatric Association and of the Royal College of Physicians, London. She wrote many research papers, participated in numerous professional meetings, and was the author of two books: The Capacity for Emotional Growth, 1970, and, with William Meissner, Basic Concepts of Psychoanalytic Psychiatry, published posthumously in 1973, She died unexpectedly on November 22, 1970.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection consists of biographical data, personal and professional correspondence; ERZ's lectures and course notes; published papers and reviews, and unpublished papers.
Folders in this collection are arranged as follows:
1-2: Biographical data
3-27: Correspondence
28-55: Lecturese
56-95: Published papers
96-107: Reviews
108-147: Unpublished papers
CONTAINER LIST
Carton 1: 1-40v
Carton 2: 41-91
Carton 3: 92v-145
Box 4: 146-160
INVENTORY
- Curricula vitae, obituary and memorial service, 1.
- Certificates of appointment, 2.
- Personal correspondence, 3-5:
  - 1943-1953: from Ernest Jones and other British psychologists, 3.
  - 1962-1970, 4.
  - Frances Hannett Gittelson, 5.
- Professional correspondence, 6-27:
  - 1956; includes Melanie Klein, 6.
  - 1957, 7.
  - 1958-1959, 8.
  - 1962, 9.
  - 1964, 10.
  - 1965, 11.
  - 1966, 12.
  - 1967, 13.
  - 1969, 14.
  - 1970, 15.
  - McLean Hospital, 1958-1963, 16.
  - McLean Hospital, 1963-1965, 17.
  - Massachusetts General Hospital, 1962-1964, 18.
  - Fred Pine, 1960-1961, 19.
  - Masud Khan, 1968-1970, re: The Capacity for Emotional Growth and other books, 20.
  - Re: Psychotherapy Study Center for post-residency training in psychotherapy, 21-27:
    - 1964, 21.
    - 1966, 22.
    - 1966-1967, 23.
    - ERZ's 60th birthday gifts to Center, 1967, 24.
    - 1968-1969, 25.
    - 1969-1970, 26.
    - 1970-1971, 27.
- Dated lectures, course notes, 28-45:
  - Simmons, 1957-1960, 28.
  - Simmons College, 29v.
  - Boston Psychoanalytic Society and Institute, 1958-1963 (I), 30.
  - BPSI, 1958-1963 (II), 31.
  - 1959-1962, 32.
  - Residents Lectures, 1960, 33.
  - Basic Concepts of Psychoanalytic Theory, Seminar, 1962, 34.
  - Harvard Medical School, 1964, 35v.
  - HMS, 1965, 36v.
  - Harvard College: Social Relations 186, 1965, 37.
  - Advanced Dreams, 1966, 38.
  - Depression I, 1966, 39v.
  - Basic Concepts, 1966, 40v.
  - Depression, 1967, 41.
  - HMS. First Year Teaching, 1968: The Basic Concepts of Psychoanalytic psychiatry, 42.
  - Depression I and II, 1968-1969, 43.
  - Basic Concepts of Dynamic Psychiatry, 1968; includes term papers., 44.
  - Clark University, 1970, 45.
- Undated lectures, course notes, 46v-55:
  - "J.N.R.", 46v.
  - "J.N.R.", 47v.
  - Notes on/So-Called Good Hysteric/ Depression/Harvard, 48v.
  - Discussion Meissner/ Harvard Course, 49v.
  - Brandeis Lecture, 50.
  - Object Relations I and II, 51.
  - Theoretical Basis of Dynamic Psychology, 52.
  - Early lectures (I), 53.
  - Early lectures (II), 54.
  - Buenos Aires/ Talk to B.A. Candidates, 55.
- Printed papers, including drafts and correspondence. Titles are ERZ's., 56-95v:
  - An unusual neurosis following head injury, 1946, 56.
  - Anxiety and the Capacity to bear it, 1949, 57.
  - The changing functions of the psychiatric outpatient department, 1949, 58.
  - Psychoanalytic observations regarding the dynamic effects of prefrontal lobotomy, 1952, 59.
  - The dynamic basis of supervision, 1953, 60.
  - The depressive position, 1953, 61.
  - The traditional psychoanalytic technique and its variations, 1953, 62.
  - The concept of anxiety in relation to the development of psychoanalysis, 1955, 63.
  - Current Concepts of transference, 1956, 64.
  - An approach to the relation between concept and content in psychoanalytic theory, 1958, 65.
  - Ernest Jones: his contribution to psychoanalytic theory, 1958, 66.
  - Introduction to symposium on depressive illness, 1960, 67.
  - The problem of accreditation, 1960, 68.
  - Suitability for psychoanalysis: A review of one hundred supervised analytic cases, 1960, 69.
  - Melanie Klein, 1882-1960, 1961, 70.
  - Symptom formation and character formation, 1964, 71.
  - Discussion of the paper by Herbert Rosenfeld, Object relations of the acute schizophrenic patient, 1964, 72.
  - The use and misuse of psychoanalysis in psychiatric evaluation and psychotherapeutic practice, 1965, 73.
  - Dynamics of the metapsychology of the aging process, 1965, 74.
  - The effects of psychotherapy, 1965, 75.
  - The theory of therapy in relation to a developmental model of the psychic apparatus, 1965, 76.
  - The predisposition to depression, 1966, 77.
  - Drugs or psychotherapy, 1966, 78.
  - In Memoriam: Max Gittelson, 1902-1965, 1966, 79.
  - Additional notes upon a case of obsessional neurosis: Freud 1909, 1967, 80.
  - Long-term treatment of chronic schizophrenia, 1967, 81.
  - The so-called good hysteric, 1968, 82.
  - Repression of traumatic experience and the learning process, 1968, 83.
  - The teaching of dynamic psychiatry, 1968, 84.
  - The analytic process, 1968, 85.
  - 96 Gloucester Place, 1969 re: The London Institute of Psychoanalysis, 86.
  - Sleep and dreaming, 87.
  - Introduction to psychoanalysis and philosophy, 1970, 88.
  - The relationship of defence to affect and its tolerance, 1970, 89.
  - Introduction to book, "Basic concepts of psychoanalytic psychiatry", 90.
  - A developmental approach to the borderline patient, 1971, 91.
  - Selected reprints, 92v.
  - The Capacity for Emotional Growth, 1970, 93v.
  - ERZ and William Meissner, Basic Concepts of Psychoanalytic Psychiatry (1973), 94v.
  - Die Fahigkeit zu Emotionalem Wachstum, 95v.
- Reviews, including drafts and correspondence, 96-107:
  - Recent British approaches to problems of early mental development, 1955, 96.
  - Envy and gratitude: A study of unconscious sources by Melanie Klein, 1958, 97.
  - Psychoanalytic concepts of depression by Myert Mendelson, 1961, 98.
  - The significance of the adaptive hypothesis for psychoanalytic theory and practice, 1963, 99.
  - Introduction to the work of Melanie Klein by H. Segal, 1965, 100.
  - Personality structure and human interaction by H. Guntrip, 1966, 101.
  - Psychosis and the very young infant, review of Psychotic states by H.A. Rosenfeld, 1967, 102.
  - Psychoanalytic supervision by J. Fleming and T. F. Benedek, 1967, 103.
  - Psychoanalysts in training - selection and evaluation by H. R. Klein, 1967, 104.
  - The psychoanalysis of dreams by A. Garma, 1968, 105.
  - The technique and practice of psychoanalysis by R. R. Greenson, 1969, 106.
  - Review of Second thoughts by Bion, 1969, 107.
- Unpublished papers, comments presented at conferences; including drafts and correspondence, 108-147:
  - Criteria for analyzability, 1959, 108.
  - A clinical approach to nosology, 1959, 109.
  - Aggression and the theory of symptom formation, 1961, 110.
  - Depression and the aging process, 1962, 111.
  - Workshop on Melanie Klein, 1962-1963, 112-115:
    - I Correspondence, 112.
    - II Correspondence, 113.
    - VII Tape transcriptions, 114.
    - IV Report, 115.
  - Panel: The psychoanalytic theory of therapy, Dec. 1963, 116.
  - Fischer paper: discussion, 1963, 117.
  - Discussion of Schur paper, 1963, 118.
  - Conference at Swampscott, May 1964, 119.
  - Training analysts, Chicago, 1964, 120.
  - International conference on psychotherapy, 1964, 121.
  - BPSI, discussion of Dr. Waelder's paper, May 1964, 122.
  - BPSI, discussion of Dr. Stein's paper, 1965, 123.
  - APA Therapeutic Alliance, 124.
  - "Depression and object loss," APA panel, 1965, 125.
  - Discussion of "Real and reconstituted past," 1966, 126.
  - Discussion of Kernberg's "Borderline personality," 1966, 127.
  - Baltimore, 1966, 128.
  - "The initial interview," panel, 1966-1967, 129.
  - Character formation in adolescence, discussion, 1967, 130.
  - Discussion of Engel's paper, "Research in psychoanalysis," 1967, 131.
  - Smith College School of Social Work, discussion, 1967, 132.
  - Discussion, APA panel in depression, 1968, 133.
  - Modell's aging and psychoanalytic theory of regression, 134.
  - Discussion of Weinberger's paper, 1968, 135.
  - Discussion of Myerson's paper, 1968, 136.
  - Topeka, 1968, includes care notes, 137.
    CLOSED UNTIL 2033.
  - Meissner's Dreaming as process, 1968, 138.
  - Aggression and symptom formation, 1968, 139.
  - Panel on non-verbal communication, 1968, 140.
  - Action, acting out and the symptomatic act, 1969, 141.
  - Sandler and Joffee: Towards a basic psychoanalytic model, International Psychoanalytic Congress, 1969, 142.
  - Psychoanalysis and the ghetto, 143.
  - BPSI panel, June 1970, 144.
  - Symposium: Psychoanalytic concepts and women today, Oct. 1970, 145.
  - International psychoanalytic conference, 1970, 146.
  - Psychoanalysis and the American Woman, 1971, 147.
- Undated and unpublished papers, 148-160:
  - Criteria for the selection of women medical students, 148.
  - Notes on Lewin and elation, 149v.
  - Use and abuse of dynamic concepts in classical psychology, 150.
  - Middle age: its problems and its challenge, 151.
  - Discussion: Peter Wolff, 152.
  - Reality trauma and reality sense, 153.
  - General discussion: research aspects of supervised psychoanalysis, 154.
  - Therapeutic alliance in the psychoanalysis of the hysteria, 155.
  - "Randall's paper." notes, 156v.
  - Metapsychiatry and social environment, notes, 157v.
  - Neurosis in the women's services, [1940s], 158.
  - Early paper on Ricardo, 159.
  - Nature and function of fantasy..., 1943-1944 (not by ERZ), 160.
Additional catalog entries
Jones, Ernest; Khan, Masud; Klein, Melanie, 1882-1960; American Psychiatric Association; American Psychoanalytic Association; Boston Psychoanalytic Society and Institute; Harvard Medical School; Massachusetts General Hospital; McLean Hospital; Psychiatrists; Psychoanalysts; Simmons College School of Social Work